<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>1dom</title>
  <subtitle></subtitle>
  <link href="1dom.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="1dom.io/"/>
  
    <updated>2022-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  
  <id>1dom.io</id>
  <author>
    <name>1dom</name>
    <email>dom@1dom.io</email>
  </author>
  
    
    <entry>
      <title>Please write a blog post</title>
      <link href="1dom.io/posts/2020-06-please-write-a-blogpost/"/>
      <updated>2020-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>1dom.io/posts/2020-06-please-write-a-blogpost/</id>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
      <p>This is my first published personal blog post in a long time. Like I'm sure most people in and around tech have, I've threatened to do this for too long. Here's some of the hows and whys, in hope that you'll do the same, if you haven't already.</p>
<h2>Don't get hung up on the how</h2>
<p>I've thought about blogging a lot before. My mistake is normally focusing too much on how to do it, rather than just getting a post published. <a href="https://www.fast.ai/2020/01/16/fast_template/">fast_template</a> offered a quick and simple way. Maybe...</p>
<p>If you're reading this, then it's because that post is sufficient to achieve the core point of a blog - get some info out there.</p>
<h2>1 thing published is better than 0 things published</h2>
<p>If it's not published and readable by others, it's not a blog, it's a personal diary. Realising this made me realise I have a lot of half complete personal diaries over the years.</p>
<p>A personal diary has its place, but it has a different set of benefits to a blog. 2 Notable benefits of a published blog vs an unpublished personal diary:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>External Feedback:</strong> without external feedback, you're missing out opportunities to learn and improve. Whilst there are benefits to introspection and personal diarying, if you already think 2+2 is 3, you're probably not going to tell yourself that it's actually 4. <a href="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Cunningham%27s_Law">Cunningham's Law</a> suggests that the internet will if you give it chance.</li>
<li><strong>Informing Others</strong> Nobody else benefits directly from the writing down of knowledge in a personal diary. If just 1 person reads this post, and gets even the slightest bit of benefit, entertainment, or motivation, that means <em>multiple people</em> have received direct value from me publishing this. &quot;More than 1 person benefits&quot; seems generally more beneficial to everyone than &quot;1 person benefits&quot;.</li>
</ol>
<p><em>&quot;But I just need to get another couple of pages done!&quot;</em> - No you don't. 1 page published is infinitely better than 0 pages in achieving the above.</p>
<h2>Everyone is different - you won't know until you try</h2>
<p>I haven't had a personal blog in probably over a decade. I might be wrong, maybe it's better not to publish, maybe nobody wants to read what you or I have to think or say. A lot of people won't want to. There's possibly even 1 or more people who only have stuff to share that literally <em>nobody else on the planet</em> could get any kind of benefit from.</p>
<p>However, those people are probably in the minority: there are a lot of broad minded folks who take many forms of benefit from many different things people have to share.</p>
<p>The only way you will know if your content is better published or unpublished is to publish it and find out - don't trust what anyone else says on this, me included!</p>
<h2>I want interesting things to read - it makes everything better</h2>
<p>This is a purely selfish point, but I hope most people agree in the same selfish way. I want interesting things to read. The more people who post personal blogs about their hobbies, interests, passions and professions, the more likely I am to have something interesting to read.</p>
<p>I want you to have more interesting things to read too, so then you're more engaged, interesting, knowledgeable, skilled and open minded when we get the pleasure of interacting. It makes my life easier.</p>
<p>If you've not published a blog before, and you've got at least one half complete website with one pretty much finished but not published post, <em>just do it!</em></p>
<h2>tl:dr;</h2>
<p>I published a blog post, and I think you should too. The primary purpose and benefit of a published blog is to get info out there. That is what has the chance to make me a better and more educated person, people other than me better and more educated people, and everyone has a chance at a slightly more interesting life. Who wouldn't want those things? It's not too hard with Github Pages and fast_template.</p>

    ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    
    <entry>
      <title>AWS CLI Tab Completion</title>
      <link href="1dom.io/posts/2020-06-aws-autocomplete/"/>
      <updated>2020-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>1dom.io/posts/2020-06-aws-autocomplete/</id>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
      <p>If you work with AWS, you've probably used the AWS CLI. It's a command line tool for interacting with Amazon Web Services.</p>
<p>Despite having used AWS for years, I only recently made it down to the <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/cli/latest/userguide/cli-configure-completion.html">end of the config section of the AWS CLI docs</a> and learned that it's possible to setup tab completion:</p>
<pre class="language-bash"><code class="language-bash">✔ ~/codeexperiments/1dom <br><span class="token number">12</span>:33 $ aws dynamodb describe-t<span class="token operator">&lt;</span>PRESSED TAB<span class="token operator">></span><br>describe-table      describe-table-replica-auto-scaling     describe-time-to-live </code></pre>
<p>With AWS CLI v1, autocomplete only extends to service names, API actions and some parameters:</p>
<pre class="language-bash"><code class="language-bash">✔ ~/codeexperiments/1dom <br><span class="token number">12</span>:33 $ aws dynamodb describe-table --<span class="token operator">&lt;</span>PRESSED TAB<span class="token operator">></span><br>--ca-bundle              --cli-connect-timeout    --cli-read-timeout       --endpoint-url           --no-sign-request        --profile                --table-name<br>--cli-auto-prompt        --cli-input-json         --color                  --generate-cli-skeleton  --no-verify-ssl          --query                  --version<br>--cli-binary-format      --cli-input-yaml         --debug                  --no-paginate            --output                 --region </code></pre>
<h2>AWS CLIv2</h2>
<p>If you haven't already, I'd highly recommend <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/cli/latest/userguide/install-cliv2.html">upgrading to AWS CLI v2</a>. You probably won't notice much difference day-to-day but it has a <a href="https://github.com/aws/aws-cli/blob/v2/CHANGELOG.rst">bunch of helpful extra little features</a>, including SSO CLI management.</p>
<p>It also expands the autocompletion functionality to include resource names! If your AWS CLI has valid credentials, you can tab complete specific resources in the account that your credentials are configured to access:</p>
<pre class="language-bash"><code class="language-bash">✔ ~/codeexperiments/1dom <br><span class="token number">12</span>:33 $ aws dynamodb describe-table --table-name <span class="token operator">&lt;</span>PRESSED TAB<span class="token operator">></span><br>1domio-statelock</code></pre>
<h2>Setup</h2>
<p>The AWS docs are pretty comprehensive on <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/cli/latest/userguide/cli-configure-completion.html#cli-command-completion-configure">how to set up autocomplete with various shells and OS.</a></p>
<p>For my personal laptop setup (Fedora 32 &amp; bash), I was able to squash the process to a oneliner. If you're using bash, and <code>aws</code> is in your $PATH, you can probably enable autocomplete with just this:</p>
<pre class="language-bash"><code class="language-bash"><span class="token builtin class-name">echo</span> <span class="token string">"complete -C '<span class="token variable"><span class="token variable">$(</span><span class="token function">which</span> aws_completer<span class="token variable">)</span></span>' aws"</span> <span class="token operator">>></span> ~/.bashrc</code></pre>
<p>If you're using something other than bash, then I'd recommend you scan through the AWS docs on setting up the CLI. The process in most cases is locate the aws_complete binary, and add a line to your shell setup that adds that binary as an autocompleter.</p>
<h2>tl:dr;</h2>
<p>AWS CLI has tab completion support, even down to resource names. <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/cli/latest/userguide/cli-configure-completion.html">Go read the AWS docs for instructions on setting it up,</a> or use the oneliner above if you're using bash.</p>

    ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    
    <entry>
      <title>Switching from Jekyll to 11ty</title>
      <link href="1dom.io/posts/2021-10-switch-to-11ty/"/>
      <updated>2021-10-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>1dom.io/posts/2021-10-switch-to-11ty/</id>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
      <p>Despite talking about how and why <em>everyone else</em> should write a blog, I have clearly ignored my own advice and instead spent time switching this blog from Jekyll to <a href="https://www.11ty.dev/">11ty</a>, a JS based static site generator. It was fun to mess around with 11ty and Github actions, and it gives me something to write about.</p>
<p><strong>NOTE</strong>: <em>I originally wrote this around Sept/Oct '21. I've been playing with eleventy internally, but only just got round to pushing and publishing Jan '22.</em></p>
<h2>Why change from Jekyll</h2>
<p>There's no right or wrong software to use in most cases. I feel a good piece of software shouldn't get in the way. Jekyll can get in the way by being quite slow as a result of being bloated with age. In Jekyll's defence, it was also largely my own lack of time and patience for Ruby that contributed to the change.</p>
<p>Jekyll was nice when it worked, but I had a few different issues getting it to build with certain plugins and settings in Github actions vs my local machines, and fixing often found me Googling basic Ruby stuff.</p>
<p>I spend my personal and professional time nerding around - I know how much I don't know, and I don't know Ruby. It's probably not hard to learn, but I just don't want to have to learn it <em>right</em> now.</p>
<h2>Why change to 11ty</h2>
<p>I do a lot of writing and note taking in markdown, and 11ty is also a markdown based static site generator, like Jekyll.</p>
<p>I write a bunch of Typescript and Javascript for my day job. It's not my favourite language, but I'm more fluent in it than most other languages these days. 11ty is written in Javascript, so it all feels a lot more familiar to me. It's also a lot quicker, lighter, smaller and easier for me in general compared to Jekyll.</p>
<p>11ty is also one of the newer static site generators, and I like shiny new thing.</p>
<h2>For the indecisive: running Jekyll and 11ty together</h2>
<p>Just in case I wanted to go back, I extracted my 2 - 3 posts from Jekyll into a separate folder outside the Jekyll hierarchy. I then setup <a href="https://github.com/yinkakun/eleventy-duo">eleventy-duo</a> and symlinked the posts folder in there. In github, I now also have 2 actions: one which builds Jekyll, one which builds 11ty, set to build when either CMS or posts are updated.</p>
<pre class="language-yaml"><code class="language-yaml"><span class="token key atrule">name</span><span class="token punctuation">:</span> Eleventy<br><br><span class="token key atrule">on</span><span class="token punctuation">:</span><br>  <span class="token key atrule">workflow_dispatch</span><span class="token punctuation">:</span><br>  <span class="token key atrule">push</span><span class="token punctuation">:</span><br>    <span class="token key atrule">paths</span><span class="token punctuation">:</span><br>      <span class="token punctuation">-</span> eleventy<span class="token important">*/**</span><br>      <span class="token punctuation">-</span> posts</code></pre>
<p>(I also include <code>workflow_dispatch</code> in most actions so I can kick them off via github UI if needed.)</p>
<p>I was hoping to be able to get them both working flawlessly together, I created separate Github Action workflows for Jekyll and 11ty, triggering each on changes to its own folder. However, minor differences around post handling thwarted me: I had to manually move the post dates from the filenames into the frontmatter for 11ty.</p>
<p>It probably is possible to get 11ty to use Jekyll's post dates, or vice-versa, but I'd already decided I preferred 11ty - and it was hardly a vast anthology of posts to manually update - so there was no need to get the Jekyll side working. I might pick it up again later if I try another static site generator.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>11ty powers this blog now. It's faster and newer than Jekyll, and a lot easier if you're familiar with JS. Ultimately, both are markdown based static site generators, so it's easy to migrate. It's probably possible to have a fully working hybrid where the same set of content markdown files power a few different static site generators to see how they compare, but that's overkill here, for the time being.</p>
<p>I'm starting to feel like these sorts of migrations and tech stack swaps are almost a right of passage for anyone exploring static site generators - especially for a personal blog!</p>

    ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    
    <entry>
      <title>Free legacy Google Domain Apps is going away. Degoogle, selfhost more.</title>
      <link href="1dom.io/posts/2022-02-google-domain-apps-going/"/>
      <updated>2022-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>1dom.io/posts/2022-02-google-domain-apps-going/</id>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
      <p>My main internet account is my Domain Apps account from 2007. It provides me with all the standard Google tools (Mail, Calendar, Docs etc.) and basically enterprise Google for a custom domain, free of charge. The service isn't going away completely - there is an &quot;upgrade to paid&quot; option - but the use of a custom domain on free services is. Whilst all good things come to an end, this one is going to be particularly painful for me.</p>
<p><a href="https://support.google.com/a/answer/60217">The G Suite legacy free edition will no longer be available starting July 1, 2022.</a></p>
<h2>My &quot;legacy Google Domain Apps&quot; account has been my primary account for ~15 years</h2>
<p>I moved my personal domain onto Google Domain Apps around November 2007 - it is by far one of the longest running internet accounts I have. The only service I have that predates it is the domain registration itself (which is still on my Dad's account as it was my 11th birthday present!)</p>
<p>I always knew this could happen, so I tried to minimise my usage of &quot;sign in with Google&quot; and other more complex service offerings, but with apparently limited success. I still haven't figured out the full impact: I need to verify what happens with my contacts, calendar events, subscriptions, channels, music, playlists, TV &amp; films, apps, files, documents, spreadsheets and the myriad of other features my Google account has acquired over the decades.</p>
<p>Since these types of accounts were only available up until 2012, anyone in this position is going to be having to unpick 10+ years of usage - you are not alone.</p>
<h2>I read about this from Arstechnica before Google</h2>
<p>Sorry to be the bearer of bad news if you're impacted by this and this is the first you're reading of it. The first I read of it was from <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/selfhosted/comments/se7ht8/good_news_legacy_g_suite_users_will_be_able_to/">this Reddit post</a>. This article talks about how Google notified people a week ago, and has had a lot of push back, so is relenting somewhat:</p>
<p><img src="/images/google-apps-article.png" alt="Arstechnica article, published 01/27/2022, 6:50 PM"></p>
<p>This is the first e-mail I have to my Google hosted e-mail explaining the changes:</p>
<p><img src="/images/google-apps-email.png" alt="E-mail from Google, published 01/27/2022, 11:25 PM"></p>
<p>The e-mail was sent after the follow-up article on the change. From the comments, I wasn't the only one to hear late.</p>
<h2>This is probably happening for agility and money</h2>
<p>Any nerd with one of these accounts over the past few years probably has a tale or 2 of not being able to use particular services because of weird legacy domain account quirks. The intent and implementation of these accounts has changed over the decades as Google morphed Google Domain Apps into GSuite and then into Workspace. Maintaining backwards compatibility can be hard, and pre-2012 accounts have inevitably gotten a little messy and consequently expensive.</p>
<p>It would be interesting to know if Google's increase in popularity and revenue over 20 year has outpaced the increase in upkeep costs of these accounts.</p>
<p>Regardless, an obsessive focus on always trying to make the latest and greatest things often requires some of the not so latest and not so greatest things to be put out of their misery. &quot;Very Agile&quot; some say, pivot, fail fast etc. Cynically: this is because they're not making enough money, but in reality, I clearly benefit from Google's new products, otherwise I wouldn't have gotten so locked-in. So it's probably both agility and money, and I benefitted from that, until I didn't.</p>
<h2>Google do this a <em>lot</em>, normally to less popular things I don't use</h2>
<p>Not only is there a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Google_products#Discontinued_products_and_services">wiki page section on discontinued services</a> but an <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Category:Discontinued_Google_services">entire Wikipedia category on discontinued Google services.</a></em> This says to me that I've been incredibly lucky to have not been hugely inconvenienced by Google discontinuations so far.</p>
<p>I should remember not to not get too comfortable with Google services, or any service that isn't mine. If I can't choose when the service stops, then then it's not mine and in an ideal world, I shouldn't make it part of my core infrastructure.</p>
<h2>Moving forward: a blessing in disguise, an opportunity to diversify and selfhost more.</h2>
<p>I really enjoy self-hosting my own software and services where possible. I enjoy the learning, and the independence, and the warm fuzzy productivity feelings. I wish I could go onto say how I'm going to replace <em>all</em> of my Google dependencies with self-hosted alternatives. However, hosting services that involve other people is different for me - that turns it from a fun hobby into another obligation. E-mail in particular, falls into that category.</p>
<p>Regardless, this can still be seen as an opportunity to diversify: the situation is so much more challenging and stressful because my Google account has become a single point of failure for multiple services. It's been worrying and useful to be forced to think about how much of my daily online life is through Google.</p>
<h2>Some alternatives needed for calendar, app store and paid content.</h2>
<p>For e-mail, I'll most likely look for an alternative e-mail provider. I don't expect my e-mail for free (keeping up with modern anti spam technologies needed to keep e-mail flowing deserves recognition!) but I'd rather not pay Google for it. I have no good reason for this want-to-not-pay-Google, other than hurt feelings. I will also try and do better avoiding using my e-mail provider as my identity provider (so no more &quot;Sign in with Google&quot;.)</p>
<p>For file management, I already make heavy use of <a href="https://syncthing.net/">syncthing</a>, so I'll move any existing storage (including camera backup) over to that. I've already got that configured also with an incremental offsite backup with <a href="https://restic.net/">Restic</a> and <a href="https://www.backblaze.com/b2/cloud-storage.html">B2</a>.</p>
<p>I'll also look into calendar options, as well a degoogled mobile phone options with my next phone upgrade. I don't know yet if switching to alternative app stores would solve content lock in completely, but FOSS oriented alternatives like <a href="https://f-droid.org/">F-Droid</a> look like they should. There's also de-googled android options to consider too, like <a href="https://e.foundation/">/e/</a> and <a href="https://www.lineageos.org/">LineageOS</a>.</p>
<h2>DuckDuckGo has improved!</h2>
<p>I haven't given <a href="https://duckduckgo.com/">DuckDuckGo</a> a try in about 5 years either, but in a totally-not-bitter-response-to-being-asked-to-pay, I've installed the DDG browser extension and switched my default search provider.</p>
<p>Last time I tried this, I lasted a few days before getting frustrated that DuckDuckGo wasn't able to read my thoughts like Google. This time, however, I've not really noticed a real drop in search quality. Although I do miss Google's cached page link alongside search results. DuckDuckGo's solution is a <a href="https://help.duckduckgo.com/duckduckgo-help-pages/features/cache/">!cache bang</a> which is just a slightly less convenient way to get to the same (Google powered ¬_¬) thing.</p>
<h2>Credit where credit's due, Google is pretty good.</h2>
<p>As hard done by and personally attacked as this Google decision has made me feel, that's because they've provided such fundamental services to me. I've tried other e-mail providers for various reasons, and few have come close to gmail in terms of speed, accessibility, antispam, convenience and integration. The frustration in this post is a testament to the comfort and convenience that the Google ecosystem has provided me.</p>
<p>Their services have typically been cutting edge, resilient, convenient and generally free, so thanks for that.</p>
<h2>Realistically, I will probably not be able to fully Degoogle, but I could be less dependent</h2>
<p>The only thing I can think of now without obvious non-Google options is my paid content associated with my account. Although my Google account has been such a core part of my life for 15 years, I will be surprised if I manage to get rid of it completely - I'm certain I will have overlooked something.</p>
<p>However, I will be looking to be less dependent on Google. I think it is a realistic target to be in a position where I don't need to be logged into a Google account 24/7 for a convenient personal tech life.</p>
<p>This means I will ultimately switch onto a free gsuite account, whilst self hosting some more services, or taking on one or two new regular online services where self-hosting is neither feasible nor fun.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>I'm grumpy that a great free thing I've had for 15 years is effectively holding itself ransom. I shouldn't be surprised though, Google discontinue services a lot. Whilst there's going to be some short term inconvenience, it's a nice opportunity to explore some alternatives and change approach to avoid single points of failure. Google has been good to me, but is definitely being less good to everyone compared to early 00's Google. I guess now it's time for me to try ween myself off it, and onto some more open things.</p>

    ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
  
</feed>